Okay בוקר טוב. boker tov. Today's דף daf is ע"ו. ayin vav.
We start on the very last line of ע"ה עמוד ב'. ayin
hey amud bet. We had read the משנה mishnah yesterday, and the
משנה mishnah spoke about when the פסח pesach touches the walls of
the oven, the pottery walls of the oven, if those walls are
hot, then they roast the פסח, pesach, and it's not being roasted
by the fire, it's being roasted by something else that has absorbed
heat, and then the פסח pesach is, that spot is a problem
and has to be cut away. And similarly, if some juices drop
from the פסח pesach and bounce back, so if the juices got
heated by the walls of the oven, then the juices cannot be
eaten, and then when those juices bounce back and get reabsorbed, also
it has to be cut away. So let's take a look at
the גמרא. Gemara. אתמר, itmar, was taught. And now actually today's דף
daf has two important principles, one on עמוד א' amud aleph and
one on עמוד ב', amud bet, that are central principles for כשרות
kashrus issues. So it's interesting that they're here in the middle of
פסחים. Pesachim. So let's take a look. חם לתוך חם דברי הכל
אסור. cham l'toch cham, divrei hakol assur. If you have something hot
falling into something hot, let's say I don't know, a hot piece
of meat falling into hot milk, or a hot piece of חזיר
chazir falling into a stew, then everybody says it's forbidden, then the
fact is both things are hot and
heat causes a transfer of taste. It doesn't exactly tell you how
hot,
basically we פסקן pasken that it's יד סולדת בו, yad soledes bo,
which is, you know, hot enough that if it was liquid you
would stick your hand in, you couldn't hold your finger in for
more than a few seconds without having to yank it out. Whatever
that is, 110 degrees, 115 degrees, something like that.
Some ראשונים Rishonim say that that's how hot you need to cook
things, but for כשרות kashrus the issue is not cooking, it's heat
enough to cause the transfer of taste, which is actually a lower
threshold. Nevertheless, we rule that it's יד סולדת בו. yad soledes bo.
So if everything is hot, so of course taste transfers. Now,
צונן לתוך צונן דברי הכל מותר, tzonen l'toch tzonen, divrei hakol mutar,
everybody says it's permissible. So basically, I mean a simple example of
something non-absorbent, let's say you have your apple that falls into, you
know, that falls into, I don't know, some חזיר chazir stew that's
cold, or some חזיר, chazir, I don't know, whatever,
cold חזיר, chazir, or let's say just milk, you rinse it off
and you're fine, you know, it's all just on the surface. Now,
if one of the things is absorbent, it obviously could be different
because it could actually get absorbed in the skin. But the basic
rule is that if things are cold then stuff, you know, at
most just,
maybe is a film on the surface and just needs to be
rinsed off. So basically it's permissible, it's not a problem. Now, what
if, however, it's one of the objects is hot and one is
cold? חם לתוך צונן וצונן לתוך חם, cham l'toch tzonen v'tzonen l'toch
cham, if something hot falls into something cold or something cold falls
into something hot, so again, let's just say a hot piece of
meat falls into cold milk, or a cold piece of meat falls
into hot milk, so what's the story? רב אמר עילאי גבר. Rav
amar ila'i gavar. רב Rav says the top one wins out. So
if the top one you go by the top one, if the
top one is cold, then what we say is that everything cools
off, right? Because you know, you understand that when you mix the
two together they meet, they reach a medium temperature.
So the גמרא Gemara wanted to understand how is it that when
two things hit and they're different temperatures they reach a medium temperature,
what exactly happens? Now, we know what happens is that the heat
gets transferred to the cold thing and it gets distributed. But the
גמרא Gemara imagined that it could go either way, either the heat
could get transferred or the cold could get transferred and the cooling
could go and cool off the hot thing, and the גמרא Gemara
assumed that it would matter, it might be a general rule based
on which is on the top, which is on the bottom. So
according to רב, Rav, it always goes by what's on the top.
If the top is hot, then it heats up the bottom thing
and everything rises in temperature. But as it's heating up the bottom
thing, that transfer of heat causes a transfer of taste and it
would be a problem. If the top is cold, then it cools
off the bottom thing and everything is going down in temperature, there
would be no transfer of taste. שמואל Shmuel would say it would
be the reverse based on what's on the bottom. So therefore, according
to רב, Rav, if the top is hot it's a problem, if
it's cold it's not a problem, according to שמואל Shmuel as we're
about to see, it's the reverse.
ושמואל אמר תתאי גבר, v'Shmuel amar tata'i gavar, the bottom one wins
out. So if the bottom is hot, then it's heating things up,
it's heating up the top stuff and that's a problem, the heat
causes transfer, but if the bottom is cold, everything is okay. Alright,
so that's the debate and this is a very important halachic question
להלכה, l'halacha, which one do you go by? So let's take a
look how we explain it based on how we bring in the
משנה. mishna. I should say yeah, besides the point that basically we
know that in terms of the way physics works it's heat that
transfers, we also know that heat rises. So if you would have
to pick one, you would pick שמואל Shmuel that says תתאי גבר,
tata'i gavar, that you go more by the bottom, and it's actually
true, because if the hot thing is on top and the cold
thing is on the bottom, the heat from the top thing is
more going up into the air rather than as much going down.
Well, I
don't... it's not our knowledge that impacts the פסק, psak, the פסק
psak was made before we knew that, but at least I could
say fortunately it's consistent with our knowledge of physics, yeah.
But I was wondering... okay.
All right, well sometimes in כשרות Kashrus we pursue positions that don't,
you know, coincide with our understanding of physics, but here at least
ברוך השם Baruch Hashem to a certain degree they do. All right,
so now the גמרא Gemara tries to prove it. תנן, Tnan, we
taught in a משנה. Mishna. נטף מרותבו על החרס וחזר אליו. Nataph
merutvo al hacheres vechazar elav. If a little bit of, three lines
from the top ע"ו עמוד א', ayin vav amud aleph, a little
bit of the juices of the פסח Pesach drops from the פסח
Pesach onto the pottery and then bounces back into the פסח, Pesach,
you have to cut off from the פסח Pesach where you think
the juice, you know, like a depth in order to get out
the juices because the juices are now improperly roasted. They're not roasted
directly by the fire, they're roasted by the hot pottery. Says the
גמרא, Gemara, קא סלקא דעתך, ka salka daitakh, יטול מקומו. yitol mekomo.
You have to take away, remove the area where it fell into,
you know, cut away the part of the skin of the פסח.
Pesach. So the גמרא Gemara says like this, קא סלקא דעתך, ka
salka daitakh, we assumed בחרס צוננת, becheres tzonenet,
that we're talking that the pottery starts off being cold. So then
what's the problem if you have hot juices, hot gravy hitting cold
pottery? So בשלמא לרב, Bishlama le-Rav, it works according to רב Rav
דאמר עילאה גבר, d'amar ila'ah gavar, the top one wins out. משום
הכי, mishum hachi, יטול מקומו. yitol mekomo. We get why when it
bounces back you have to cut away a piece of the פסח.
Pesach. Why? דאזיל רותבא, de'azil rutva, that the gravy goes, it drops
from the פסח, Pesach, it hits the pottery, מרתח ליה לחרס. meratach
lei lacheres. Now what happens when hot gravy hits cold pottery? So
since it's coming from above, it heats up the pottery because רב
Rav says עילאה גבר. ila'ah gavar. So the pottery now gets heated
up. והדר חרס ומרתח ליה לרותבא, vehadar cheres umeratach lei lerutva, then
the pottery gets so hot, which is surprising because even if it's
heating it up, you would assume it heats it up
to a temperature that is somewhere midpoint between the pottery and the
gravy. But the גמרא Gemara is assuming the gravy is coming from
the top, it heats up the pottery a good deal. Now the
pottery is so hot that it's hot enough to roast the gravy.
והדר חרס ומרתח ליה לרותבא, vehadar cheres umeratach lei lerutva, now it
goes and it roasts the gravy. וכי הדר רותבא אפסח, vechi hadar
rutva apesach, and now when the gravy goes back to the פסח,
Pesach, קמטלי ליה לפסח מחמת חמימותא דחרס, kamatli lei lePesach machmas chamimusa
decheres, the פסח Pesach is being roasted by the heat of the
pottery. Or you could just say even more simply, the gravy which
is now not כשר kosher because that's been heated through the pottery
is now being absorbed into the פסח. Pesach. רחמנא אמר, Rachmana amar,
the Torah says צלי אש, tzelih esh,
roasted by the fire ולא צלי מחמת דבר אחר, velo tzelih machmas
davar acher, not roasted by something else. So we get why that's
a problem. אלא לשמואל דאמר תתאה גבר, Ela leShmuel damar tata'ah gevar,
but according to שמואל Shmuel that says the bottom one wins out,
why is there a problem at all? חרס, Cheres, the pottery, כיון
דצונן הוא, keivan detzonen hu, if it's cold and the gravy is
hitting it from above which is hot, so according to שמואל Shmuel
the bottom one wins out, אקורי מיקר ליה לרותבא, akorei meikar lei
lerutva, the pottery should be cooling off the gravy. אמאי יטול מקומו?
amai yitol mekomo? Why do you have to do anything about cutting
it away from the פסח? Pesach? The gravy never got heated by
the pottery.
I don't know if that's clear, but let's try to maybe graphically
show it.
Okay, so anyways here we'll do like this. רב Rav says you
go by the
top and שמואל Shmuel says you go by the bottom, right? תתאה
גבר. tata'ah gavar. So according to רב Rav basically if you have
hot on top and let's say it falls into a cold liquid,
what happens is is that this heats it up and that's going
to be אסור assur because the heat transfers. So in the reverse
case if you have cold something falling into something hot, right, so
it cools it. So that looks like it cools the heat. Okay
and that's going to be מותר mutar because then heat doesn't transfer
because everything is being cooled down. And according to שמואל, Shmuel, it's
the reverse. If you have hot going into cold, then what happens
is is that cools
and it's going to be מותר. mutar. And if you have cold
going into hot, right, then that's going to heat up and it's
going to be אסור. assur. Okay, so that's the difference between עילאה
תתאה ila'ah tata'ah according to רב Rav and שמואל. Shmuel. Now, what's
the story
with the פסח? Pesach? So if you've got here your פסח Pesach
on the fire, okay, and it's being heated... well it was heated
up let's say now it's off the fire. That's confusing because this
is supposed to be a fire that's supposed to be a liquid.
Anyway, okay you've got your פסח Pesach and you have your pottery
here, okay, your חרס. cheres. So if the gravy drips down and
the gravy is hot, right, so according to שמואל Shmuel what happens?
The gravy is hot, it's coming from the...
so let's start with רב, Rav, okay. So here's
your pottery, okay. So the gravy drips down, it's hot, okay, it
heats up, now you have hot pottery, so then this becomes hot,
then this goes
ahead and
this... But according to שמואל, Shmuel, it goes down and everything cools
off. So if everything cools off, right if this is cooling off
the gravy, then who cares if the gravy bounces back? The gravy
was never heated up by anything else other than the fire and
it should not be a problem. So that's the גמרא'ס Gemara's question.
So it says תא שמע גבר חרס כיון דצונן הוא,
Ta shma gavar cheres keivan
detzunen hu, since the pottery is cold, קרי מיקר ליה לרוטב, karei
meikar leh lerotev, it cools off the gravy. אמאי יקמוץ מקומו, Amai
yikmotz mekomo, why do you have to now cut the gravy away
from where it got absorbed into the פסח? Pesach? So the גמרא
Gemara says כדאמר רב ירמיה אמר שמואל בסולת רותחת, Kiddamar Rav Yirmeyah
amar Shmuel besolet rotachat,
that he's going to say in a minute by the next part
of the משנה, Mishnah, where it talks about dripping into flour, that
we're talking that the flour itself was boiling. הכא נמי בחרס רותחת,
Hacha nami becheres rotachat, here too, you're wrong, the pottery wasn't cold,
the pottery was hot. So therefore if the pottery was hot and
the gravy is hot, then everybody agrees that it's a problem, because
whether you go by the top or the bottom, if you've got
hot pottery, the pottery is going to heat up the gravy, and
therefore the gravy will be אסור. asur. It bounces back into the
פסח, Pesach, you have to cut it away. Okay. And now we're
going to look at the second part of the משנה Mishnah that
is basically the exact same point made with the flour. תנן, Tnan,
we taught later in the משנה. Mishnah. נטף מרוטבו על הסולת, Nataf
merotevo al hasolet, some of the gravy drops not on the pottery
but on some flour. So now it doesn't bounce back because flour
absorbs rather than it's not a hard surface, but you've got a
problem now because you want to actually eat the flour. But the
flour has in it פסח Pesach gravy. Why is that a problem?
Because again, if the פסח Pesach gravy is cooked by the heat
of the flour and not by the heat of the fire, so
then the gravy inside of this flour is not able to be
eaten. So it says you have to remove that area where it
dripped into.
Clearly we're seeing gravy is like part of the פסח Pesach as
opposed to...
Right, that's, and that's correct, right we're treating the gravy and the
requirements of the meat of the פסח, Pesach, we're treating, applying it
equally to the gravy. So you have to then remove the area
of the flour where the gravy dripped into. So קא סלקא דעתך,
Ka salka dach, we're assuming בסולת צוננת, besolet tzonenet, that the flour
is cold. בשלמא לרב דאמר עילאה גבר, Bishlama leRav damar ila'ah gevar,
according to רב Rav you say you go by the top, I
understand why the gravy becomes problematic when it drops into the flour.
משום הכי יקמוץ מקומו, Mishum hachi yikmotz mekomo, you have to now
remove the area it dripped into, דמרתח לה
לסולת, demartach lah lasolet, because what happens? The hot gravy which is
coming from the top heats up the cold flour והדר הדרא vehadar
hadra that surrounds it, והדר, vehadar, and then the גמרא Gemara says
הדר חוזר, hadar chozer, חוזר chozer can mean around it like, you
know, or it could mean and then it goes back.
והדרא סולת, vehadra solet, and now once the flour is heated up
by the dripping gravy, now the hot flour goes ומרתח לה לדידה,
umartach lah ledideh, heats up the gravy that's inside of it, וקא
מיטוי רוטב מחמת חמימותא דסולת, veka mitvei rotev machamat chamimuta desolet, and
the gravy is now being heated by the heat of the flour,
ורחמנא אמר צלי אש ולא צלי מחמת דבר אחר, veRachamana amar tzli
esh velo tzli machamat davar acher, and the תורה Torah says heat
it by the fire, not heated by something else, even if that
something else was in turn heated by a fire. So that's the
problem. Same issue. It heated up the flour and the flour is
heating up the gravy. אלא לשמואל דאמר תתאה גבר, ela l'Shmuel de'amar
tata'ah gavar, but according to שמואל Shmuel that says you go by
the bottom, בסולת כיון דצוננת היא, besolet keivan detzonenet hi, since the
flour is cold
and the hot gravy is dipping into it, what happens? Everything just
cools off and there should be no problem. יקורי קא מיקר ליה,
Ikorei ka meikar leh, it should cool off the gravy. למה לי
יקמוץ מקומו, Lama li yikmotz mekomo, why do you have to remove,
you know, take away the space where it dripped into? It shouldn't
be a problem at all. Well skip the parentheses. So אמר רב
ירמיה אמר שמואל, Amar Rav Yirmeyah amar Shmuel, so says רב ירמיה
Rav Yirmeyah in the name of שמואל, Shmuel, בסולת רותחת, besolet rotachat,
and we're talking about the boiling hot flour. Like we said before,
we applied this answer to the case of the pottery, here's where
it was originally said in the case of the flour, that we're
talking not that it fell into something cold, it fell into something
hot, whether it was hot pottery and that roasted the gravy, or
whether it was hot flour and that roasted the gravy. But either
way, this is not relevant to the debate of רב Rav and
שמואל Shmuel because you don't have to assume one was cold and
one was hot, you could assume they were both hot, and the
problem is that the gravy is being roasted by something else. I
should just say that תוספות Tosafot discusses that what if the thing
is already roasted, then the additional roasting it would get by touching
the pottery would not be a problem, אין בישול אחר בישול? ein
bishul achar bishul?
Yeah exactly, a type of אין בישול אחר בישול. ein bishul achar
bishul. So we have to be assuming that the thing that's hitting
it is not itself fully roasted. Anyway תוספות Tosafot tries to deal
with that issue and work it into the cases in the משנה.
Mishnah.
Yes. Can the gravy that drips into this flour, is there any
kind of ביטול bitul that applies?
In theory, but especially if the area where it right now dripped
is you can, it has a gravy taste, which it definitely will,
right you get some nice meat juice falling in flour, it's going
to taste in that area. So but yes, in theory ביטול bitul
could apply.
So even if it was like this huge thing, it would you
would still...
Well that's why I said you just focus on the immediate place
where it fell.
No, but even ביטול bitul could apply?
It wouldn't apply to the immediate place. In that immediate
place...
Exactly. Okay, סתם.
stam. Okay, now
we can’t really prove it from our משנה Mishna because our משנה
Mishna could easily go be assumed that everything is hot, but we’re
going to try to prove it now from the end of the
משנה, Mishna, not the beginning.
סך בשמן של תרומה, sach ba'shemen shel terumah, you now sort of
put on oil, you anointed it, that’s the wrong word, you rubbed
on oil, תרומה terumah oil onto the פסח. Pesach. And this is
assumed that the פסח Pesach might be hot, might be cold, and
you’re rubbing on oil. אם חבורת כהנים יאכלו, im chavurat kohanim yochlu,
if it’s a group of כהנים, kohanim, no problem, they can eat
the פסח Pesach with the absorbed תרומה terumah oil. אם של ישראל,
im shel Yisrael, however, if it’s non-כהנים, kohanim, then
אם חי הוא, im chai hu, if it’s raw, the פסח, Pesach,
ידיחנו, yadi'chenu, rinse it off, because as we said, cold on cold
you can just rinse off, and therefore it’s not a problem. So
yeah, you had some a film of תרומה terumah oil on the
surface, but just rinse it off. אם צלי הוא, im tseli hu,
if it’s roasted, now roasted could be hot or could be cold.
Okay, but even if it’s cold roasted, it’s absorbent, and therefore you
can’t just rinse it off, right? It’s nice and soft and absorbent.
You wouldn’t say that if some טרף treif fell on a sponge,
you know, just rinse off the surface of the sponge. It gets
absorbed into it.
It would be a little harder if this is צלי. tseli.
Ah, that’s true, צלי tseli is not the same as like boiled,
that’s true. Anyway, okay, we’ll speak more about what types of cold
things are absorbent.
But isn't it now being cooked by the oil and not directly
by the fire?
No, everything is cold.
No, but if I have my שמן תרומה shemen terumah and I’m
a כהן, kohen, they said I don't have to do anything, right?
But so I’m putting the שמן, shemen, if I’m putting this whole
thing on the fire, the oil is getting hot.
Right. So that’s an interesting question, like at what type of stuff
is considered—on the one hand the גמרא Gemara was so concerned that
the little bit of moisture that comes off of certain types of
wood sticks would make it like בישול, bishul, and here it doesn't
be—isn't concerned that a little bit of oil makes it sort of
like בישול. bishul. So it’s not exactly clear at what status something
is considered to be negligible. Presumably the גמרא'ס Gemara's discussion before about
the sticks was just like a לכתחילה, l'chat'chila, but it’s still a
good legitimate question, which is why לכתחילה l'chat'chila are we so מקפיד
makpid on what type of stick do you use and we don't
care about like some oil which is—exactly. It is a very good
question. Again, maybe possible difference is that here it first gets absorbed
and then gets put on the fire so it’s not seen of
as something different, it’s already got incorporated into the פסח. Pesach. But
it is a good question, like at what stage is something so
negligible or incorporated that it’s no longer relevant for that issue. So
anyway, let’s see what it now goes on to say. אם צלי
הוא יקלוף את החיצון, im tseli hu yiklof et hachitzon, if it’s
roasted, then you have to peel off the outer peel, the outer
layer, because that absorbed this oil that cannot be eaten by non-כהנים.
kohanim. Now let’s understand the issue. בשלמא לרב, bishlamah l'Rav, now the
גמרא Gemara understands that the צלי tseli is whether it is cold
roasted and is just natural absorbency, it’s roasted but cold and it’s
natural absorbency, or roasted and hot, it also includes that case. So
let’s understand this. בשלמא לרב, bishlamah l'Rav, it works according to רב,
Rav, that you go by the top thing, the top thing here
presumably is the oil, which is cold.
דאמר עילאה גבר, de'amar ila'ah gavar, you go by the top. אמטו
להכי, amtu lahach, once you come along to this, סגי ליה בקליפה,
sagi lei biklifah, it’s enough to remove just the top
a peel, just a peel. משום דעילאה צונן הוא, mishum de'ila'ah tzonen
hu, the top which is the oil is cold, and therefore the—even
if the bottom meat is hot, it’s not going to affect anything,
everything will just cool off and the only thing you have to
worry about is an outer—is peeling off the top layer because that
got absorbed through natural absorbency. אלא לשמואל Ela le-Shmuel דאמר תתאה גבר,
d'amar tata'ah gavar, but שמואל Shmuel that says you go by the
bottom, so if the פסח Pesach is not just roasted but it’s
hot, so that should mean make everything hot. And therefore כיון דחם
הוא, kivan de'cham hu, since the פסח Pesach is hot, מיבלע בלע,
mivla bala, it should absorb like normal hot things absorb, which we
don't say when hot things get mixed up you just peel off
a layer, we say it absorbs throughout. So if the bottom is
hot and it heats up the oil, it should absorb throughout the
פסח. Pesach. אמאי סגי ליה בקליפה, amai sagi lei biklifah, why is
just peeling off the outer layer enough? נאסר לגמרי, nitssar legamrei, the
entire פסח Pesach should be forbidden to non-כהנים kohanim because the oil
should be absorbed throughout, since it’s considered all hot. So the גמרא
Gemara says no, שאני סיכה דמשחו בעלמא הוא, shani shicha de'mashu be'alma
hu,
you know, rubbing oil is different, it’s only a tiny little bit,
it doesn’t totally transfer throughout the entire פסח. Pesach. Now of course
it’s very nice, wouldn’t that be nice if that was like a
normal הלכה halakha of כשרות? kashrut? We’d just say oh, a little
bit fell on, you don't have to worry, you know, it couldn't
have absorbed too much, it’s only a little, just peel off the
outer amount. Now part of the issue here also is is that
even though the bottom is hot and we'd say the bottom wins
out, it's not directly over a fire. One would imagine if you
had your פסח Pesach directly over fire and you were smearing it
with this תרומה terumah oil, right, but putting aside my first question
that it should be a type of a frying or cooking, that
if it’s directly over the fire we would be concerned that it
would go throughout. But this is just retained heat in the meat
of a פסח Pesach and it’s a little bit of an oil.
So there the גמרא Gemorah says even assuming that it's considered to
be the hot winds, the little oil does not go deeper than
the קליפה, kleipah, than the outer shell. Again, how exactly can you
quantify what's a little and when would you say that it's not
clear. Okay, but the גמרא Gemorah basically says you can't prove anything
from our משנה. Mishnah. Either the case is that everything is hot,
the pottery or the flour, and in this case here with the
oil on the roasted פסח Pesach that it doesn't get absorbed more
than a קליפה, kleipah, we'll say even if the פסח Pesach is
hot and it should have gotten absorbed more since it's only a
little bit, we don't have to worry any deeper than a קליפה.
kleipah. Okay, so we haven't proven either way רב Rav or שמואל
Shmuel according to our משנה. Mishnah. Let's take a look now as
we quote a ברייתא Braitah that supports שמואל. Shmuel.
Is there a question? Yeah. When we say this transfusion in a
case of חם לתוך חם אסור, cham l'toch cham assur, do you
mean like instantaneously? Like let's say you put it in there, can
you reach it out right away or would you say...
Yeah, we for כשרות Kashrus it is true logically things should take
time, but since we actually can't measure we do assume instantaneously. But
you're right, logically it shouldn't happen instantaneously. Especially you could imagine if
you touch the thing and the other one is still cold, so
yeah.
But what we talked about gravy splattering and jumping back.
Right. And that's instantaneous, yeah.
Yeah, and this is this is a more sustained application of the...
Yeah, and your point is is that how come by the gravy,
how come this is not as problematic as the gravy? Well, by
the gravy also we just sort of said
יטול את מקומו, yitol et mekomo, but it is true what's exactly
your question? Why here is it enough to do the קליפה kleipah
and the gravy we had
to... Right. So that's a good question because יטול
את מקומו yitol et mekomo normally the way the ראשונים Rishonim explain
it is
קליפה, kleipah, when we say remove a קליפה, kleipah, it's the thinnest
amount that can be taken off with it remaining like one piece,
you know, but like it could be a micron thin in theory.
I mean if you had one of those like really thin deli
slicers, you know, as thin as possible where it all remains one
piece. יטול את מקומו yitol et mekomo is considered to be deeper.
יטול את מקומו yitol et mekomo is considered to go in like
about the, you know, like the like the thickness of a thumb
or something like that or, you know, whatever, like a half... no,
it's not an inch, I don't know, a centimeter or something, but
it's considered to be it's or half an inch, it's considered to
be deeper. So it is a good question why with the gravy
bouncing back, we assume it gets in deeper than when you smear
the oil where we assume that it remains on the surface. Yeah,
I don't know. I don't have a good answer to that, unless
saying that the gravy is fattier than the oil, you know, oil
is they're both liquids but the gravy is fattier. All right, so
now the
גמרא Gemorah says like this.
Yeah, and תוספות Tosfos alludes to it on ע"ה עמוד ב Ayin
Hey Amud Beis if you look at תוספות, Tosfos, he says יטול
את מקומו ולא סגי ליה בקליפה לפי שהרוטב נבלע יותר בתוכו. yitol
et mekomo v'lo sagi lei b'kleipah l'fi she-harotev nivla yoter b'tocho. I
mean he doesn't exactly explain why, he acknowledges the difference. I think
you have to say because gravy is fattier than the oil, the
תוספות Tosfos acknowledges that there is that difference. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemorah continues like this.
תניא כוותיה דשמואל, Tanya kivasei d'Shmuel, second wide line. We taught a
ברייתא Braitah like שמואל. Shmuel. חם לתוך חם אסור וכן צונן שנתן
לתוך חם אסור. Cham l'toch cham assur v'chein tzonen she-nasan l'toch cham
assur. If the bottom thing is hot, it's a problem. So hot
into hot or cold into hot it's a problem. So that's like
שמואל, Shmuel, the bottom one wins out. חם לתוך צונן Cham l'toch
tzonen however, hot into cold, וצונן לתוך צונן v'tzonen l'toch tzonen or
cold into cold, since the bottom one is cold, מדיח madiach just
rinse it off. So that's a straight ברייתא Braitah like שמואל, Shmuel,
which is why I said we wind up ruling like שמואל Shmuel
for תתאה גבר. tata'ah gavar. But now the גמרא, Gemorah, right, when
it's, you know, when it basically has a straight ruling like שמואל
Shmuel pulls back a little bit and says it can't be that
everything is just hunky-dory if the bottom one is cold. I don't
know. So the גמרא Gemorah says like this. חם לתוך צונן מדיח,
Cham l'toch tzonen madiach, hot into cold all you have to do
is rinse off, which is what we've been assuming up until now
according to שמואל. Shmuel. How can you say that? כיוון דחם הוא,
Keivan de-cham hu, since at least one of them is hot even
if it's just the top one, so אדמקר ליה ad-mekar lei as
the bottom thing is cooling it off, אי אפשר דלא בלע פורתא,
ee efshar d-lo bala porta, there is still some heat, you know
it takes time, this is the idea of time, to cool things
down and some of the heat from the thing on the top
should, you know, cause the bottom to absorb something from the top.
So it's true it's not heating up the bottom but everything is
in the process of cooling off, something should be happening, something should
get absorbed into the bottom. So קליפה מיהא ניבעי, kleipah miha nibei,
let's at least require a קליפה, kleipah, if we don't say that
it gets fully absorbed, at least have to take off that outer
shell, that point of contact. Especially now the גמרא's Gemorah introduced the
idea of קליפה, kleipah, so now maybe it can ask this question.
If there's a concept of קליפה kleipah a little bit even if
things are cold like we said before potentially, so if even if
the top one is hot at least a קליפה kleipah should be
required. So the גמרא Gemorah says you're right, let's switch the text
of the ברייתא. Braitah. אלא אימא, Ela eima, a radical change of
the text now because... Marks out like there's nothing forcing it to
say this except logically it feels you can't have a complete leniency
if one of them is hot. אלא אימא Ella eima say the
following: חם לתוך צונן, cham l'toch tzonen, if it's hot into cold,
קולף, kolef, then you have to do a קליפה, klipa, remove an
outer layer. צונן לתוך צונן, tzonen l'toch tzonen, cold into cold, מדיח,
mediach, you rinse off. Okay, תניא אידך, tanya idach, we taught another
ברייתא braita the exact same thing. בשר רותח שנפל לתוך חלב רותח,
basar roteach shenafal l'toch chalav roteach, not חלב, chelev, חלב, chalav, hot
meat fell into hot milk, וכן צונן v'chen tzonen וכן צונן שנפל
לתוך חם, v'chen tzonen shenafal l'toch cham,
or cold meat that fell into hot milk, so the bottom one
is hot, אסור, assur, it's all forbidden, the bottom one wins out.
חם לתוך צונן, צונן לתוך צונן, cham l'toch tzonen, tzonen l'toch tzonen,
however, if the bottom is cold, whether it's hot into cold or
cold into cold, מדיח, mediach, you rinse it off. Now again, a
straight ruling like שמואל, Shmuel, but the גמרא Gemara pulls back. חם
לתוך צונן מדיח? cham l'toch tzonen mediach?
Hot into cold you all you have to do is rinse off?
Hot meat falls into cold milk? What do you mean? כיון דחם
הוא, keivan d'cham hu, since the meat is hot, אדמיקרי ליה, ad-m'karei
lei, as the cold milk is cooling it off, אי אפשר דלא
בלע פורתא, ee efshar d'lo bala purta, some of the taste in
the meat is going to get absorbed, it's going to get absorbed.
קליפה מיהא בעי, klipa miha ba'ei, you should at least require a
קליפה, klipa, or some of the cold, some of the milk would
be absorbed in the meat, some of the meat should be absorbed
in the milk and some of the milk should be absorbed in
the meat because the meat is still hot and it's taking time
for it to cool off. So the גמרא Gemara says you're right.
אלא אימא, Ella eima, here's how you have to read it. חם
לתוך צונן, cham l'toch tzonen, hot into cold, קולף, kolef, you have
to remove an outer like an outer layer because although it's being
cooled off while it's hot there's some transfer of taste. צונן לתוך
צונן, tzonen l'toch tzonen, cold into cold, מדיח, mediach, you rinse off.
So basically a straight ruling like שמואל Shmuel that the bottom wins
out, but then the גמרא Gemara pulls back and says even שמואל
Shmuel would agree to רב Rav that you would have to remove
a piece, an outer shell. The difference of רב Rav and שמואל
Shmuel is if the one that's hot wins out. For שמואל Shmuel
the bottom, for רב Rav the top. Then it's like everything is
hot and then it causes a complete transfer. But if the one
that's cold is the one that wins out, the bottom is cold
according to שמואל, Shmuel, if the other thing is hot at least
there'll be a minimal transfer and at least you'll have to do
a קליפה. klipa. Now תוספות Tosafot asks an interesting question.
What happens תוספות Tosafot says in this case where hot piece of
meat falls into cold milk, we rule like שמואל, Shmuel, so you
need to do a קליפה. klipa. So you do a קליפה klipa
about the, from the, of the point of contact you remove a
thin layer of the meat. What about the milk? How do you
remove, how do you do a קליפה klipa of the milk? So
תוספות Tosafot says two opinions. One is and one is you have
to do שישים shishim opposite the קליפה, klipa, and the other, meaning
you estimate if the point of contact would have been, you know,
I don't know, one cube, you know, would have been like a
centimeter by a centimeter and a קליפה klipa is I don't know
a tenth of a centimeter, we've defined that that's the thickness of
a קליפה, klipa, then it would be, you know, 0.1 cubic centimeters
of we say that of the milk is problematic and then you
need to do שישים shishim opposite it.
And in a case where it's,
no, all the milk is mixed together so you have to שישים.
shishim. Anyway, רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam says the whole idea of קליפה
klipa when the bottom one is cold is all a דרבנן חומרא.
d'rabbanan chumra. Basically we rule like שמואל Shmuel that if the bottom
is cold nothing happens. So the whole need of קליפה, klipa, you
know as we see it was a thing the גמרא Gemara introduced
at the very end, so that whole need is only a rabbinic
concern and therefore if it's something like a liquid, which it's not
possible to do a קליפה, klipa, just forget about it. So that's
what he says. If it's the meat you have to remove it
obviously because you can do a קליפה, klipa, but if it's something
that קליפה klipa isn't possible then you can just forget about it.
Now there's another interesting question I should say. Meaning you don't need
the milk is totally fine. You have to do a קליפה klipa
on the meat, but the milk is totally fine because it's not
possible to do a קליפה klipa on the meat.
So you just forget about it?
Yeah because he says the whole requirement of קליפה klipa is rabbinic
because basically the bottom one is cold, the bottom wins out. The
גמרא Gemara introduced the idea of קליפה klipa at the end. It's
only rabbinic. So if it's not possible to do it, meaning not
in general, if it's hard to do a דרבנן d'rabbanan forget about
it, like if you cook chicken and milk we can't say oh
well I'd have to throw it out so forget about it, you
know, no. But the nature of קליפה klipa he says is really
only a חומרא chumra and therefore they didn't require it when קליפה
klipa wasn't possible to be done. That's what רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam
says. Another interesting question is that if you think about it, if
the meat falls into milk and it's a big bowl of milk
then it winds up after a while that the milk is on
top of the meat and the meat is on the bottom, right?
So why don't we say that the bottom one is the meat
and that's hot and whatever? So the ראשונים Rishonim basically say, you
know, you have to assume that it basically goes from like how
they initially came in contact even if afterwards the liquid winds up
going over, leads to interesting questions. Another related question is how do
you deal with the issue of עירוי, iruy, of pouring boiling water
onto something? Right if I take my kettle and I pour it
onto something, right a straight boiling stream of water, well why don't
we say let's say I've got my boiling milk here and I
get take it off the fire and I pour it straight onto
my... meat, we say, oh, not a problem, שמואל Shmuel תתאה גברא,
tata'ah gavra, so everything is okay, at most what you need is
a קליפה. klipah. So this is an interesting question about the status
of עירוי, iruy, and actually it's a big debate in תוספות Tosafot
how עירוי iruy fits into this discussion of תתאה גברא, tata'ah gavra,
and I'll just tell you the simple answer is to distinguish between
a stream that's interrupted and uninterrupted. As long as I'm pouring from
the kettle and it's an uninterrupted stream and it's going back to
the kettle which was directly on the fire, then we don't say
this תתאה גברא. tata'ah gavra. Then we say it's uninterrupted, it's from
the source of heat or the thing that was on the fire,
and then the stream, this boiling hot milk hitting the meat is
going to win out. None of this תתאה גברא tata'ah gavra nonsense,
I don't know, for as long as it's hitting it. Okay, but
if I let's say do something and then I break it, right,
I do a little drop and then I, you know, and then
I straighten up my kettle and then the hot milk is hitting
without an attach to the kettle, that's when we're going to say
תתאה גברא. tata'ah gavra. So it's an interesting question of how to
fit this into a whole discussion of עירוי.
iruy. So you've had that whole day?
Presumably.
Okay, let's now continue.
And then, you know, where does like לח בלח lach belach or
יבש ביבש yavesh beyavesh fit into this?
Yeah, so I'll, yeah, so this sort of assumes like I said
that the easiest scenario here is that they're both hot, okay, they're
both solid, right, and that's most of the cases here is that
they're both solid. Okay, but it could theoretically apply to liquids as
well, that's where it gets into the עירוי iruy question, which is
why I raised it.
If you have a small pot full of hot water or something,
right, and you empty the entire pot eventually it's...
Well
that's the other question, which is goes back to Michael's point of
the whole day. Do we say that if it keeps on hitting
and hitting and hitting, you know, unrelentingly hitting it, then that also
changes the whole scenario, it's not just a one-time contact. So yeah,
all that stuff does get discussed, and the answer is that it
does make things different. But we do see here in the case
at the end by the milk that it applies to liquids as
well. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this, so that
was one major יורה דעה Yoreh De'ah concept, which is עילאה גבר
ila'ah gevar or תתאה גבר, tata'ah gevar, the way we rule. Now
the גמרא Gemara continues. אמר מר, Amar Mar,
so we just talked, we'll go back to what we said before.
צונן בצונן מדיח, tzonen be-tzonen medi'ach,
if it's cold into cold all you have to do is rinse
it off. So אמר רב הונא, Amar Rav Huna, said רב הונא,
Rav Huna, לא שנו אלא שלא מולחו, lo shanu ela she-lo malcho,
it's only or מולחו, malcho, it's only if you did not salt
it. So when is it enough to rinse something off if it's
cold? If one of the pieces, let's say the piece of meat
that's hitting the milk, it's unsalted meat. מולחו? mulocho?
Okay, so much for my grammar,
more like חריף charif that kind of thing?
Yeah, אבל מולחו, avel malcho, if you salted the meat, so אסור,
assur, it's forbidden, then the meat is absorbent and it absorbs the
milk that it fell into. How do you know? דאמר שמואל, de-amar
Shmuel, because שמואל Shmuel says מליח הרי הוא כרותח, maliach harei hu
ke-rote'ach, something salted is like something that is boiling, that is very
hot, and therefore the same way something hot absorbs, something that is
salted absorbs. Now I should say though, okay, I'll just leave it
at that for now. Okay, כבוש הרי הוא כמבושל, kavush harei hu
ke-mevushal, and if something is a pickle
that's like it is cooked. Okay, so we're focusing on the first
part, מליח. maliach. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, הא דאמר שמואל מליח הרי
הוא כרותח, ha de-amar Shmuel maliach harei hu ke-rote'ach, that statement of
שמואל Shmuel that salted is like it's boiling, לא אמרן אלא שאינו
נאכל מחמת מלחו, lo amran ela she-eino ne'echal machmat malcho, it's not
any salted, it's only salted so heavily that it could not be
eaten. So what רש"י Rashi just says it means, because they would
salt things to preserve it, so you would salt it more, you
know, to the point past it being edible, and then you'd have
to rinse off the salt. So רש"י Rashi says it means that
it's a little bit extra salted. תוספות Tosafot says that it means
very very heavily salted like you would salt stuff like if you
were, you know, you were that you were that you were no,
that you would be salting it really to preserve it for a
long time, and you'd really have to like, you know, really like
submerge it in water and get out the salt. אבל נאכל מחמת
מלחו, avel ne'echal machmat malcho, if it's not salted so much and
it is fit to be eaten, לא, lo, that would not be
considered so hot, that would not be problematic, and it would just
be like it's cold and all you'd have to do would be
rinse it off.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this, ההוא בר גוזלא
דנפל לכדא דכמיכא. hahu bar gozala de-nafal le-khadda de-kamcha. So you had
a certain pigeon that fell into some of this כמיכא, kamcha, which
is like this, you know, milk like a sour cream type of
a or, you know, dip or cottage cheese type of a dip.
Okay, and the pigeon was salted to get out the blood. So
שרייה רב חיננא בריה דרבא מפשרוניא. sherayei Rav Chinana berei de-Rava mi-Pashrunya.
So this רב חיננא Rav Chinana permitted it and said just rinse
off the pigeon. So אמר רבא, Amar Rava, מאן חכים למישרא מילתא
כי האי, man chakim le-mishra milta ki hai, who would be so
smart to permit something like this? אילאו רב חיננא בריה דרבא מפשרוניא,
ilav Rav Chinana berei de-Rava mi-Pashrunya, were it not for this רב
חיננא, Rav Chinana, he was smart enough to figure out that you
could allow this even though it's a salted pigeon, דגברא רבא הוא,
de-gavra rabba hu, he's a great תלמיד חכם. talmid chacham. אמר לך,
amar lach,
and he'll say to you, כי אמר שמואל מליח הרי הוא כרותח,
ki amar Shmuel maliach harei hu ke-rote'ach, when did שמואל Shmuel say
that salted is like it's boiling, that's when שאינו נאכל מחמת מלחו,
she-eino ne'echal machmat malcho, it's so salted that it's not fit to
be eaten. האי, hai, but this pigeon נאכל מחמת מלחו, ne'echal machmat
malcho, is able to be eaten even with the salt and therefore
this problem that Shmuel discussed. Okay. והני מילי, vehani milei, when is
this true? חי, chai, if it is—meaning when is it true? So
now we said when it's cold, all you have to do is
rinse off,
exception number one is unless it's very heavily salted. Now, exception number
two to the rule, that if it's cold just rinse it off,
is it's only true if it's cold and it's raw. אבל צלי,
aval tseli, going back to our Mishna, if it's roasted, even if
it's cold, then בעי קליפה, ba'ei klipah, then you do have to
remove an outer shell because even though everything is cold, it is
absorbent. Okay. ולא אמרינן, velo amrinan, and when do we say that
a קליפה klipah is enough if it's cold? אלא דלית ביה פילא,
ela deleit bei peila, only if there are no like cracks and
crevices, so even if it absorbs it only absorbs into the outer
shell. אבל אית ביה פילא, aval it bei peila, if there are
cracks and crevices, then in that case אסור, assur, we do say
that the milk—assuming we're saying a piece of meat fell into milk—that
the milk would get in even deeper, even further. And number two,
ומתובל בתבלין, umetubal betavlin, and if it's heavily spiced, so again, similar
to being salted, even if it's cold, אסור, assur, it's forbidden because
that causes it to be very absorbent.
So there's a rule, meat, yes, cold
meat can be absorbent if it's falling into a liquid, it's not
falling onto another solid, it's falling into a liquid. So this becomes
an interesting הלכה halacha that things are a little bit
more looked at circumstantially and not just by this strict rule. The
basic rule is, is that heat transfers things, other things do not,
and therefore cold, just rinse it off. But then we get to
these exceptions, salted, so we say we make salted a pseudo heat,
salted is like hot, and therefore it still follows the rule that
heat transfers. Okay, but then, and then only salted to a certain
point, but then the גמרא Gemara starts pointing out, you know what,
there are times when things will get absorbed even without heat. If
you have a liquid and you have the solid is absorbent, who
needs heat? And therefore it starts talking about the fact that if
it's not raw, if it's been roasted, even if it is raw,
if it's spiced or if it's got cracks, other types of issues,
you know, that will also make it a problem.
Do all types of meat have
cracks?
I mean, that's a good question. I don't know. You think about
a steak, I mean, it depends, how much cracks are cracks, you
know, different pieces clearly have different types of ridges and cracks. Who
knows how to measure this type of stuff? Okay. Look, it's also
a question about buying your fish from a, you know, from a
supermarket. So first there's a question about identifying the fish because, you
know, any of the white fish stuff, the stuff that's not distinctive
like the salmon or the tuna, if you don't see the skin
on it, you know, you don't see the scales, you don't know
that they're not mislabeling it. And actually there have been reports, I
know, there's a lot of evidence about how that there's a lot
of intentional mislabeling of fish. But if it does have, exactly, but
if you've got the skin on it and you see the scales,
or if it's like tuna or salmon, you know, which is very
distinctive,
then you can know that it's been identified correctly. But how did
they cut it? So, you know, some people will give them like
a, you know, knife and bring in their own knives or they'll
use reserved knives. But even if they didn't, everything is just being
transferred, it's all just on the surface, it's all cold, right? And
so the real הלכה halacha is that you could just rinse it
off.
But anyway, you don't need a קליפה klipah at all?
So if you want to be מחמיר machmir you could do a
קליפה, klipah, you know, that's this question about like this גמרא Gemara
about at what stage do you say that you need a קליפה
klipah or not. Well, anyway, I mean, they have like—what? Yeah, but
the גמרא—yeah, Gemara but the גמרא Gemara was talking about that it
was cooked in ridges, not raw in ridges. So again, some of
this is exactly hard to quantify and some of this is debated.
All right. So now the גמרא Gemara goes on.
What? Yeah, but the גמרא—what? Gemara If it's cooked in ridges then
it's אסור, assur,
we're not—if it's raw meat. Yeah, but it's debated, it's debated exactly
how to match up these various criteria. Let's go on. אמר רב,
amar Rav, said Rav, I know, בשר שחוטה שמנה, basar shechuta shemena,
now we move from two very important areas of הלכה, halacha, תתאה
גבר tatta'ah gavar and מליח, maliach, and not only that, I'd say
a third area, absorbing when things are porous and cold. Now to
another very important area which is the issue of ריחא, reicha, things
transferring by smell without contact. Okay, let's take a look, which is
really the question of אדים. adim. So בשר שחוטה שמנה, basar shechuta
shemena, you have fatty slaughtered meat, שצלאו עם בשר נבילה כחושה, shetsala'o
im basar neveila kechusha, fatty kosher meat that is being roasted nearby
some lean treif meat. Okay, so nothing comes in contact. Do we
say that the smells transfer in the air and that the kosher
meat absorbs the treif meat through the air? So he says אסור,
assur, it's forbidden, even though the treif meat itself is lean and
doesn't give off too much smells and aroma. מאי טעמא, mai ta'ama,
why? מפטמי מהדדי, maptemi mehadadi, they fatten one another up, meaning that
the fatty meat from the kosher meat, the smells of it and
the goes and draws out the taste of the in the air
of the lean treif meat. meat and brings it back and it
gets absorbed into the fatty.
Why don't you say that the kosher meat is like emitting more,
it's more of an emitter than an absorber?
Okay, that's his חידוש chiddush that we would say that it does
it all. So לוי Levi אמר, amar, לוי Levi goes to the
opposite extreme. אפילו בשר שחוטה כחוש afillu basar shechuta kachush even if
the שחוטה shechted meat is lean, שצלאו עם בשר נבילה שמן she-tzla'o
im basar neveila shamen and it's the טריף treif meat that's fatty,
so then you would say that the טריף treif meat is fatty,
the whole air is filled with the smells of the fatty טריף
treif meat. Nevertheless, the kosher meat is kosher. מאי טעמא mai taama
why? ריחא בעלמא הוא reicha be'alma hu it's just smell, וריחא לאו
מילתא היא ve-reicha lav milta hi smell isn't anything, it's not considered
a transfer of taste. Only when they actually touch. Presumably what לוי
Levi would say is, although it's not clear, what happens if you
take a bite out of the kosher meat and it tastes a
little bit like the טריף treif meat? Would that be a problem?
So לוי Levi might say, he might not just be making a
argument about the physical reality, oh nothing really will happen. He might
say even if some of the smell gets absorbed, smell doesn't have
any halachic status. Okay, what we say is טעם ta'am taste, which
it comes through a contact through directly through the objects, but smell
isn't considered the thing itself, only taste is. So לוי Levi says
the kosher meat remains kosher, which basically means that ovens are not
going to be much of a problem, right? In theory according to
לוי, Levi, you could cook טריף treif and kosher meat together uncovered
in the same oven. Even לכתחילה? lechatchila?
Possibly. Let's see where the גמרא Gemara turns what the גמרא Gemara
says. אמר עביד לוי עובדא בי ריש גלותא בגדי ודבר אחר amar
avid Levi uvda be reish galuta be-gedi ve-davar acher
so לוי Levi actually ruled in a practical case in the house
of the ריש גלותא Reish Galuta that they cooked a goat in
the same oven with a pig. What they're doing cooking pigs in
the house of the ריש גלותא Reish Galuta I don't know, and
he said the goat was permissible. מיתיבי meitivei I'll ask you, here
we have a ברייתא beraita and now we'll see what it's doing
in our מסכתא. masechta. אין צולין שני פסחים כאחד ein tzolin sheni
pesachim k'echad you don't roast two קרבן פסחs Korban Pesach side by
side, מפני התערובות mipnei ha-ta'arovot because they'll get mixed up. So what
does it mean mixed up? Either you'll get mixed up whose is
whose פסח Pesach and the חבורה chaburah will eat the wrong פסח,
Pesach, or we're saying that the smells will be absorbed and who
cares if the smells is absorbed? Well, if my פסח Pesach absorbed
the smells of yours, the same way we learned before that the
הלכות halachos of roasted applies not only to the meat
but to the gravy, the same is true here. If it's considered
to contain the tastes of your פסח, Pesach, then I'm eating from
the tastes of from your פסח, Pesach, and I'm not allowed to
eat from your פסח, Pesach, only you can eat from your פסח,
Pesach, it goes by איש כפי אכלו ish kefi achlo and only
eat from its own פסח. Pesach. So don't cook them side by
side, it'll get mixed up. מאי לאו תערובות טעמים mai lav ta'arovot
ta'amim does it not mean the tastes will be mixed through transfer
through smells and therefore you're eating from somebody else's פסח? Pesach? תיקשי
ללוי tikshei le-Levi it's a challenge to לוי Levi who says smell
is not an issue. גמרא Gemara says לא lo no, that's not
what's going on, מפני תערובות גופין mipnei ta'arovot gufin we're afraid the
actual bodies of the פסח, Pesach, the
actual animals themselves, the meat itself will get mixed up and you
won't know whose is whose. גמרא Gemara says הכי נמי מסתברא hachi
nami mistabra you know what that makes sense. מדקתני סיפא mide-katni seifa
the end of the ברייתא beraita says ואפילו גדי וטלה ve-afillu gedi
ve-taleh you can't even cook a sheep and a goat next to
one another. So what do you mean even? אי אמרת בשלמא מפני
גופין ei amart bishlama mipnei gufin if the problem is that the
actual meat will get mixed up, היינו דקתני אפילו גדי וטלה hainu
de-katni afillu gedi ve-taleh that's why you have to say even a
sheep and goat because that would seem to be nothing to be
afraid of.
Why are we worried about it?
לא פלוג lo plug or whatever, but you understand why it's a
חידוש. chiddush. אלא אי אמרת מפני תערובות טעמים ela ei amart mipnei
ta'arovot ta'amim if the concern is the tastes will be transferred in
the air,
מה לי גדי וטלה מה לי גדי וגדי mah li gedi ve-taleh
mah li gedi ve-gedi why should I care if it's a goat
and a goat or a goat and a sheep? It's the same
problem, the tastes will be exchanged in the air. גמרא Gemara says
אלא מאי ela mai so what do you want to say? על
כרחך מפני תערובות גופין al korchacha mipnei ta'arovot gufin you've proven since
it had to say even a goat and a sheep that the
concern was that the actual meat would get mixed up, הוא דאסר.
hu de-asar. אבל תערובות טעמים שרי aval ta'arovot ta'amim sharei but it
was just because of the tastes transferred by the smell, that would
be permitted. So if that's how you're reading the ברייתא, beraita, let's
turn it around, לימא תהוי תיובתא דרב leima teihavei tiyuvta de-Rav let
it be a contradiction to רב. Rav. רב Rav says the taste
itself is a problem. If that's true, why was the ברייתא beraita
concerned only about the mixing of the meat? It should have been
concerned about the mixing of the tastes. אמר רב ירמיה amar Rav
Yirmiyah הכא במאי עסקינן hacha bemai askinan what are we talking about?
What's the scenario that we're only worried about the actual meat being
mixed up and not the tastes? Why is it not a problem
for
רב? Rav? כגון שצלאו בשתי קדירות kegon she-tzla'o bi-shtei kedeirot that it's
in two separate pots and therefore presumably like covered pots and therefore
the smells don't transfer in the air and it's only a problem
of mixing up the meat.
גמרא Gemara says בשתי קדירות סלקא דעתך bi-shtei kedeirot salka datchach what,
two pots? Is that possible? Why is it not possible the scenario
is cooking it in two pots?
Wait, is one
פסח Pesach in two pots? No, two פסחים Pesachs in two pots.
Why can't we talk about cooking a פסח Pesach in a pot?
Because you can't cook it in a pot because it has to
be roasted. אלא אימא ela eima fine, we don't literally mean two
pots, כעין שתי קדירות ke-ein shtei kedeirot like... What does that mean?
So רש"י *Rashi* says it means let's say
there is a mound between them and they are in sort of
the same space but they are separated so in some way in
which the smells don't really transfer from one side of the room
to the next. Okay, there is some type of a big mound
between the two and somehow there is very little transfer or no
significant transfer of smell.
Where would they physically roast the פסח Pesach *Pesach*?
Outdoors, wherever it was convenient, anywhere in ירושלים *Yerushalayim*. Anywhere? In ירושלים
*Yerushalayim*.
Okay, so והכי קאמר *ve-hachi ka-amar*, and this is how to read
it. אין צולין שני פסחים כאחד מפני התערובת *Ein tzolin shnei Pesachim
ke-echad mipnei ha-ta'aroves*. You can't cook them according to רב Rav *Rav*,
this is how you would read it, next to one another because
of mixing up. מאי תערובת *Mai ta'aroves*? What type of mixing? תערובת
טעמי *Ta'aroves ta'amei*. The first concern according to רב Rav *Rav* would
be the smells would get mixed up, which would happen in almost
every case. ואפילו כעין שתי קדרות *Ve-afilu ke-ein shtei kederos*, and you
know what? Even if you made it like two pots, you did
it in spaces and where the smells wouldn't transfer, דליכא תערובת טעמי
*de-leika ta'aroves ta'amei*, and there's no concern about the mixing of the
smells, אסור *assur* it would remain forbidden according to רב Rav, *Rav*
משום תערובת גופין *mishum ta'aroves gufin* because you'd still have to be
concerned that you get the meat mixed up, ואפילו גדי וטלה *ve-afilu
gedi ve-taleh* and for that case we have to say even a
sheep and a goat. Okay, but the simple sense works better according
to שמואל Shmuel, *Shmuel*. But what we also did learn was that
there's a case called כעין שתי קדרות *ke-ein shtei kederos* which is
not a problem even according to רב Rav *Rav*, that'll be important,
we'll get back to that. אמר רב Rav. מרי *Amar Rav Mari*,
so רב Rav, מרי *Rav Mari* says כתנאי *ke-tana'ei*, this is like
a debate of תנאים Tana'im *Tanna'im*, this debate of רב Rav *Rav*
and שמואל Shmuel, *Shmuel*. הרודה פת חמה *Ha-rodeh pas chamah*, you take
a hot loaf of bread out of the oven, ונתנה פי חבית
יין של תרומה *u-nesanah pi chavis yayin shel terumah*, and you put
it on top of a barrel of wine of תרומה *Terumah* wine.
How much do we say that the smells of the wine and
the heat of the bread draws out the smell of the wine
and it gets absorbed into the bread and now the bread has
to be treated like תרומה *Terumah* and could only be eaten by
כהנים *Kohanim*? So that's debated. רבי מאיר אוסר *Rabbi Meir osser*, רבי
מאיר *Rabbi Meir* forbids the bread to non-כהנים *Kohanim*. רבי יהודה מתיר
*Rabbi Yehuda mattir*, רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* permits it. He says it
doesn't absorb the smell of the wine. רבי יוסי מתיר בשל חטים
ואוסר בשל שעורים *Rabbi Yossi mattir be-shel chittin ve-osser be-shel se'orim*. He
says it depends on the type of the bread, if it's wheat
bread it's okay, that's not very absorbent, and if it's barley bread
that is absorbent and that is a problem, מפני שהשעורים שואבות *mipnei
she-ha-se'orim sho'avos* because the barley draws the smells and the flavor of
the wine. So you see that there's a debate, nothing is touched,
it's all transferred through air, and there's a debate whether the wine
taste is absorbed into the bread and whether it matters. So מאי
לאו תנאי *mai lav tana'ei*, is it not a debate of תנאים
Tana'im *Tanna'im*? דמר סבר ריחא reicha לאו מילתא היא *de-mar savar reicha
lav milsa hi*, the one that says it's always permissible רבי יהודה
*Rabbi Yehuda* would say smell is never an issue, ומר *u-mar*, the
other one, which would be both רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* and רבי
יוסי *Rabbi Yossi* that say that at least it's always or sometimes
a problem, hold ריחא מילתא reicha milsa, היא *reicha milsa hi* that
smell can be an issue. So it seems like it's a debate
of תנאים *Tanna'im*. ללוי ודאי תנאי *Le-Levi vadai tana'ei*, for לוי Levi
*Levi* who says that ריחא reicha *reicha* is not a problem, clearly
there are תנאים *Tanna'im* that disagree with him because there's רבי מאיר
*Rabbi Meir* and רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yossi* that say the bread is
sometimes a problem. So he has to say yeah, there are some
תנאים *Tanna'im* that feel that ריחא *reicha* is a problem. I would
go like רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* but there are תנאים *Tanna'im* that
feel it's a problem. לרב נימא תנאי *Le-Rav neima tana'ei*, do we
have to say according to רב Rav *Rav* also would he also
have to concede that it's a debate that רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda*
who says the bread is okay would disagree with him, would say
smell is not an issue? So no, not necessarily. אמר לך רב
Rav *Amar lach Rav*, רב Rav, *Rav* could tell you in principle
everybody agrees to me, דכולי עלמא ריחא מילתא reicha milsa. היא *de-kulei
alma reicha milsa hi*, everybody agrees that smell can be a problem.
It's just that not every circumstance is the same. Not every circumstance
has actual enough smell to be a problem. ולאו אתמר עלה *ve-lav
itmar alah*, look, it was said about that debate about the bread
and the wine, דההיא *de-hahi*, on that case, אמר רבה בר בר
חנה אמר ריש לקיש *amar Rabbah bar bar Chana amar Reish Lakish*,
בפת חמה וחבית פתוחה *be-pas chamah ve-chavis pesuchah*, if the bread is
hot and the barrel is open, דברי הכל אסור *divrei ha-kol assur*,
everybody says that it's forbidden because everybody would agree that the hot
bread draws out the aroma and the open barrel exposes the aroma.
And everybody would say it's forbidden. So he says you see, everybody
says רב Rav *Rav* would agree with me that in principle ריחא
מילתא *reicha milsa* as long as the circumstances are right. And if
the barrel is open and the bread is hot, everybody would say
it's forbidden. Now the reverse case, the opposite extreme, בפת צוננת וחבית
מגופה *be-pas tzonenes ve-chavis megufah*, if the bread was cold and the
barrel was sealed, דברי הכל מותר *divrei ha-kol muttar*, everybody would agree
no matter what your principle is, nothing to be afraid of there,
there's no aroma and there's no heat to be drawing it. לא
נחלקו *lo nechelku*, the debate in the משנה *Mishnah* about the bread
and the wine is in the middle case, אלא בפת חמה וחבית
חתומה *ella be-pas chamah ve-chavis chasumah*, either hot bread with a sealed
barrel, אי נמי בפת צוננת וחבית פתוחה *i nami be-pas tzonenes ve-chavis
pesuchah*, cold bread with an open barrel. And therefore they're debating whether
in those circumstances how much does the smell transfer. So רב *Rav*
says look, everybody agrees that when smell transfers it's a problem. What
they are debating is under what circumstances does
it transfer. But cases where it does transfer, everybody agrees it's a
problem. דהא נמי, the case of roasting the כשר kosher meat and
the טרייף treif meat side by side, that's כפת חמה וחבית פתוחה
דמיא, ke'pas chama v'chavis petucha damya, that's like hot bread and an
open barrel, that is a case that everybody would agree. Okay, so
now you have this debate of רב and שמואל, Shmuel not clear
how we פוסקין. paskin. The initial discussion about the פסח sounded more
like a support of שמואל, Shmuel, we don't worry about smells. This
issue sounded more to support רב that we do worry about smells.
שמואל would have to say that at least he has some תנאים
that have to, I'm not שמואל, excuse me, לוי Levi, would have
to say that he has some תנאים that at least disagree with
him. Okay, so we don't know exactly which way to פוסקין paskin
here. We have supports in both directions. Let's see how the גמרא
Gemara ends up. תני רב כהנא בריה דרב חיננא סבא, Tani Rav
Kahana brei d'Rav Chinena Sava, so רב כהנא Rav Kahana the son
of רב חיננא Rav Chinena the elder taught, פת שאפאה עם צלי
בתנור, pas she'afa im tzli b'tanur, bread that was cooked together with
roasted meat in an oven, אסור לאוכלה בכותח. assur l'ochla b'kutach. You
can't eat it with like a מילכיג milchig dip.
Now, creamy, dairy, you know, processing.
Right. Now, כמאן דהא פרו, k'man d'ha pru, how do you think
we rule based on that?
How do you think we rule based on that?
Do we rule that ריחא is a problem based on that? That
you can't eat the bread that was cooked with meat? Does it
seem to be like we rule like רב, that smell's a problem?
Well, here's the problem. If we rule like רב that smell's a
problem because we're treating the bread like פליישיג, fleishig, so it sounds
like we do rule like רב. So then you might remember what's
the הלכה halacha about פליישיג fleishig bread? פליישיג fleishig bread, you're not
allowed to eat it even with פרווה parve because we're afraid you'll
eat it with מילכיג. milchig. So some people try to bring this
גמרא Gemara as a proof that we rule like רב, that smell's
a problem. Others bring this גמרא Gemara the opposite, that it proves
like לוי, Levi if the smell were really a problem, then you
wouldn't be able to eat the bread at all. So, ah, but
if we rule like לוי Levi why is it an issue? So
this gets back to Michael's question, that maybe even לוי Levi would
agree לכתחילה l'chatchila you have to be careful. So since לכתחילה l'chatchila
you can eat this bread with פרווה, parve, don't eat it with
מילכיג. milchig. Okay, but בדיעבד, b'di'eved, if you mixed it with מילכיג
milchig according to לוי Levi it wouldn't be an issue. So whether
this ruling proves like רב or לוי Levi is not clear.
Let's read one last case. So האי ביניתא, ha'i binisa, a fish
דאיטווא בהדי בישרא d'itv'va b'hadai bisra was cooked in the same oven
together with meat. Okay, this is the problem about mixing fish and
meat. You know the problem of mixing fish and meat? It's all
based on this one line of גמרא. Gemara. Really? Yep. אסר רבא
מפרזיקא למיכלה בכותחא. Assar Rava mifarzika l'meichla b'kutcha. So רבא Rava from
פרזיקא Farzika forbade it to
be eaten together with, and what does the אטווא itv'va mean?
It was roasted. Roasted in the same place. So רבא Rava from
פרזיקא Farzika forbade it to be eaten together with the fish, together
with a מילכיג milchig dip. A similar idea, it absorbed the פליישיג
fleishig aroma. Whether it's like רב because ריחא מילתא, or whether it's
like לוי Levi. because at least לכתחילה l'chatchila you have to be
concerned. So he would not allow it to be eaten with מילכיג.
milchig. Now, the גמרא Gemara says, מר בר רב אשי אמר, Mar
bar Rav Ashi amar, מר בר רב אשי Mar bar Rav Ashi
says, אפילו במלחא נמי אסור. afilu b'melcha nami assur. You can't even
eat it with salt, meaning you can't even eat it by itself,
this fish and meat. Why? משום דקשיא לריחא, mishum d'kashya l'reicha, because
it gives you bad breath, ודבר אחר, v'davar acher, and leprosy. So
according to this, the prohibition of meat and fish is a health
issue. It's a concern of bad breath and leprosy and some health
issue and that's the problem. So I should say fish
bones and stuff like that.
No. So I want to say two things about this. So first
of all, רמב"ם Rambam never rules this הלכה. halacha. רמב"ם Rambam basically
felt that all health issues in the גמרא Gemara were wrong or
not based on medical science and not להלכה. l'halacha. So you will
never find anywhere in the רמב"ם Rambam that you can't eat fish
and meat together.
Number two, it is ruled in the שולחן ערוך. Shulchan Aruch. Okay,
because the גמרא Gemara language here is אסרי, asrei, he forbade. So
that, you know, is treated like it's not just health advice, it's
an איסור. issur. So it is ruled in the שולחן ערוך, Shulchan
Aruch, but even so, you could have said it's one thing when
they're cooked together, you know, and then maybe that creates some chemical
change in them, you know, according to this health concern. To eat
cold fish together with meat, cooked separately and chewing them together in
your mouth at the same time, that's quite a big jump from
this גמרא, Gemara, although that is our practice. One last thing getting
back to the issue of ריחא מילתא. So there's a debate of
the ראשונים Rishonim whether we rule like רב or לוי. This gets
to the issue of cooking different things, you know, מילכיגס milchigs and
פליישיגס fleishigs or כשר kosher and טרייף treif together in the same
oven. Even according to those that say we rule like רב, you
remember the גמרא Gemara says if it's שתי קדירות shtei k'deirot it's
not a problem. So if one of them is covered and the
steam cannot escape, it's okay. So that's why, for example on the
airline, you can have your כשר kosher stuff cooked with the טרייף
treif stuff as long as it is wrapped. There's no הלכה halacha
of double wrapping, the only point of double wrapping is is that
if the outer wrap gets torn, at least there's an inner wrap
to protect it.
The תוספות Tosafos goes further to say that if it's a place
that's very ventilated, like a very large oven or our ovens that
have a lot of ventilation, it could be that that's not a
problem either because then there's no, if they're not in close space
for the flavors to transfer, for the smoke, so to take a
look at תוספות, Tosafos, תוספות Tosafos says
אשרי רבא מפרזיקא, Asrei Rava MiFarzika, he says מכאן פסק רבנו תם
כרב, mikan pasak Rabbeinu Tam ke-Rav, he ruled like רב that ריחא
is a problem, ורב נמי דשרא בסי וסבס v'Rav nami deshar basi
v'seves ובבתנורים גדולים שלנו u'v'tanurim gedolim shelanu our big ovens נראה דמותר
לאפות לחם עם אותה פסטידא nira demutar la'afos lechem im osa pastida
which is a פליישיג fleishig thing, הואיל ומכוסות היטב הוי כשני קדירות.
ho'il mechusos heiteiv havei k'shnei kedeiros. If it's covered then it's okay,
so that's the idea of covering things, ואפילו פלדוניש שיש להרחיק va'afilu
paldonish she'yeish l'harchik אין נראה לרבי שיהיה אסור ein nira l'rabbi she'yehei
assur שיש אויר מרובה בתנור וההבל מתפשט. she'yeish avir merubeh b'tanur v'hahevel
mitpashet. Okay, so if there's a lot of ventilation and air, it
also could be that it is not a problem. So this is
the issue about cooking things side by side in the same oven,
let alone the question of why is it a problem to cook
things sequentially in the same oven is even more of a question
why that should be a problem and that you'll have to find
out when you learn יורה דעה. Yoreh Deah. Okay, so what about...